Finding Aid for the Peter Gena Collection of Papers and Scores, 1950-2012
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Peter Gena Collection of Papers and Scores, 1950-2012
Mus. Arc. 85
Gena, Peter
5 boxes (139 folders and items)
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Contains correspondence, writings, concert programs, articles, scores, and recordings.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Peter Gena, 2015-2018.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Peter Gena was born in Buffalo, New York, 27 April 1947. He earned his B.A. (1969), M.A. (1972) and Ph.D. (1976) degrees at the State University of New York at Buffalo where he studied composition with Morton Feldman, William Kothe, and Lejaren Hiller. From 1974 to 1976, he was a Lecturer in Music and Director of the Electronic Music Studio at the California State University in Fresno. From 1976 to 1983, he was an Assistant Professor in Theory-Composition at the School of Music of Northwestern University, where he co-directed the Computer Music Studio. From 1983-2017 he was on the faculty at the School of the Art Institute of Chicago. During his time in Chicago, Gena has produced, directed, and performed in many new musical and multi-media events, including NEMO '96, New Music America '82 in Chicago, and the 1978 International Computer Music Conference at Northwestern University. He was the Events Program Director for the 1997 International Symposium of Electronic Arts (Chicago), and was the Artistic Director of the New European Music Overseas Festival (1995-96). Gena is decorated by the French government at the rank of Chevalier dans l'Ordre des Palmes Académiques.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, writings, concert programs, articles, scores, and recordings. The content reflects Gena's work on the John Cage Reader, his work as a concert programmer, and his research interests. The score series includes six of Gena's compositions and three works by Julius Eastman.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in seven series:
I. Correspondence
II. Writings and teaching notes by Gena
III. Writings by others
IV. Programs
V. Clippings
VI. Journal issues and publications
VII. Scores
VIII. Audio and video recordings
IX. Additions
Container List
- Correspondence, 1979-2010, I.; Folder 1-31
  Contains correspondence to and from Peter Gena, or to others on behalf of Gena.
  Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - Amirkhanian, Charles, 1988-10-15, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 001)
    Letter of recommendation for Gena to Martin Prekop, School of the Art Institute of Chicago.
  - Ashley, Robert, 1988, 1992, 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 002)
  - Buckner, Thomas, 1993, 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 003)
    Letters to Buckner from Gena.
  - Cage, John, 1988-09-20, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 004)
  - Chatham, Rhys, 1992, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 005)
  - Cohen, Douglas, 1992-1994, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 006)
  - Consey, Kevin E., 1992, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 007)
  - Coover, James B., 1995, 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 008)
  - De Mare, Anthony, 1986, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 009)
    Includes a concert program and related material.
  - French American Cultural Exchange, 2010, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 010)
    Funding matters for two Partner University Fund projects: TransAtLab Research: Actual/virtual sound, space, and object and Space and objects: the new Atlantis sound
  - Gann, Kyle, 1994-01-19, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 011)
    Letter of recommendation for Gena to Carol Becker, School of the Art Institute of Chicago.
  - Gozdziewski, Marek, 1993, 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 012)
    On behalf of Centre of Contemporary Art, Warsaw, Poland.
  - Higgins, Dick, 1979-1982, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 013)
    Includes catalogs and a bio-bibliography.
  - InterArts Chicago, 1994, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 014)
    Chiefly concerning arrangements for NEMO (New European Music Overseas) festival 1995-96.
  - InterArts Chicago, 1995, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 015)
    Chiefly concerning arrangements for NEMO (New European Music Overseas) festival 1995-96. Includes organizational documents for InterArts Chicago.
  - Kubera, Joseph, 1990, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 016)
  - Lauten, Elodie, 1995-02-28, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 017)
  - Lawson, Peter, 1993, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 018)
  - Lombardo, Robert, 1995-02-21, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 019)
  - Luft, Mary, 1991-09-26, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 020)
    For Tigertail Productions.
  - Montréal Musique Actuelles, 1990-11-28, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 021)
  - Museu de arte contemoranea, 1992, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 022)
    Includes correspondence from Sylvio Continho and Christina Freire.
  - Oliveros, Pauline, 1992-12-10, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 023)
  - Pratesi, Ludovico, 1993-07-09, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 024)
    Gena to Pratesi.
  - Schubert, Barbara, 1994-02-14, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 025)
    On behalf of University of Chicago Department of Music.
  - Stäbler, Gerhard, 1993-08-04, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 026)
    Gena to Stäbler.
  - Syverud, Steven, 1995-02-15, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 027)
    On behalf of Northwestern University School of Music.
  - Terkel, Studs, 1983-04-15, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 028)
    Gena to Terkel.
  - TriQuarterly, circa 1980, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 029)
    Sent by Anne-Marie Zwierzna concerning manuscript for the John Cage Reader.
  - Williams, Jan, 1993, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 030)
  - Yim, Jay Alan, 1994, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 031)
- Writings and teaching notes by Peter Gena, 1974-1999, II.; Folder 32-48
  Contains writings that include drafts for his contributions to the John Cage Reader and notes prepared for teaching classes.
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  - After antiquity: John Cage in conversation with Peter Gena, 1982-03-31, 23 pages (Box 1, Folder 032)
  - Biofeedback in music: biomusic, 1974-11, 13 pages (Box 1, Folder 033)
    Research proposal for California State University, Fresno.
    Accompanied by Research proposal submitted to the National Science Foundation by California State University, Fresno, March 30, 1976.
  - Concert of antimusic: program notes, undated, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 034)
  - Experimental music, undated, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 035)
    Manuscript notes.
  - Fifty years after: Music of the European reconstruction and the Euro-American community, 1995, 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 036)
    In CUBE (calendar).
  - Freedom in experimental music, circa 1980, 2 copies (19 and 27 pages) (Box 1, Folder 037)
    In TriQuarterly 52 (1981).
  - Hiller notes, undated, 13 pages (Box 1, Folder 038)
    Authorship is not clear.
  - John Cage, 1912-1992, 1992, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 039)
    In New Art Examiner, October 1992.
  - John Cage Reader: Preface, circa 1980, 4 pages (Box 1, Folder 040)
    TriQuarterly 52 (1981).
  - John Cage, the composer, circa 1980, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 041)
    Three typescript versions, including one titled John Cage, a portrait of the man as (of all things) a composer. Version of the chapter in the John Cage reader.
  - Physiological approach to DNA music (excerpt), 1999, 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 042)
    Written with Charles Strom. In Ylem Newsletter, number 10 volume 19.
  - Program notes for April 5 composer's concert, undated, 1 page (Box 1, Folder 043)
    For the work, Romance, based on a work by Claude Balbastre.
  - Teaching notes for Acoustics 101, undated, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 044)
  - Teaching notes for Music A-15-1, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 045)
  - Teaching notes for Music A-15-2, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 046)
  - Teaching notes for Music A-15-3, undated, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 047)
  - Teaching notes for Music theory 102: some comments on voice-leading and chord connection, undated, 2 pages (Box 1, Folder 048)
- Writings by others, 1974-2005, III.; Folder 49-59
  Writings by other authors collected by Gena, including three texts for the John Cage Reader.
  Alphabetically arranged by author surname.
  - Brooks, William: Choice and change in Cage's recent music, circa 1980, 31 pages (Box 1, Folder 049)
    Marked with correction as prepared for the John Cage reader.
  - Burns, Kristine H.: History of electronic and computer music including automatic instruments and composition machines, 2005, 18 pages (Box 1, Folder 050)
  - Davies, P. J.: Beethoven's nephropathy and death: discussion paper, 1993, 3 pages (Box 1, Folder 051)
    In Journal of the Royal Society of Medicine, volume 86.
  - Dobrian, Chris: MSP tutorial: Tutorial 24: Analysis, using the FFT, undated, 13 pages (Box 1, Folder 052)
    Version unknown but based on original text by Dobrian.
  - Dunn, John: Life music: the sonification of proteins, 1999, 9 pages (Box 1, Folder 053)
    Written with Mary Anne Clark. In Leonardo volume 32 number 1, 1999.
  - Gann, Kyle: New music in the Second City, undated, 11 pages (Box 1, Folder 054)
  - Kostelanetz, Richard: Numbers: Poems and stories, 1974, 1 folder (Box 1, Folder 055)
  - Oliveros, Pauline: To the American Society of University Composers, 1981-04-05, 14 pages (Box 2, Folder 056)
    Caption: To the benefit of all sentient beings".
  - O'Shea, J. G.: Was Frederic Chopin's illness actually cystic fibrosis?, 1987, 2 pages (Box 2, Folder 057)
    Abstracts and citations for Chopin studies.
  - Perloff, Marjorie: Unimpededness and interpenetration: the poetic of John Cage, circa 1980, 19 pages (Box 2, Folder 058)
  - Schmitt, Natalie Crohn: John Cage's aesthetics and twentieth-century science, circa 1980, 54 pages (Box 2, Folder 059)
    Preliminary version of text titled John Cage, nature, and theater, in the John Cage reader.
- Programs, 1969-2012, IV.; Folder 60-78
  Concert programs, some including additional material, including research for the concert planning and organizational documents of the concert programmer.
  Arranged in chronological order.
  - Programs, 1969-04-11, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 060)
    Senior recital of Joseph Kubera.
  - Programs, 1974-1979, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 061)
  - Programs, 1980-01-16, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 062)
    Julius Eastman at Northwestern University.
  - Programs, 1980-1981, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 063)
  - Programs, 1982, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 064)
  - Programs, 1983, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 065)
  - Cornelius Cardew memorial concert, 1983-05-05, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 066)
    With supporting research material.
  - Programs, 1984, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 067)
  - Programs, 1985-1986, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 068)
  - Programs, 1987, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 069)
  - Programs, 1988, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 070)
  - Young, La Monte and Marian Zazeela: Sound and light environment: a time installation measured by a setting of continuous frequencies in sound and light, 1989-03-01, 11 pages (Box 2, Folder 071)
    With program notes by Young and Zazeela.
  - Programs, 1990-1994, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 072)
  - Programs, 1995-1996, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 073)
    Including NEMO events.
  - ISEA '95: 6th International Symposium on Electronic Art, 1995-09, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 074)
    Full packet, including correspondence.
  - ISEA '97: 8th International Symposium on Electronic Art, 1997-09, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 075)
    Booklet with documentation of organizing the festival in Chicago.
  - Programs, 1998-1999, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 076)
  - Programs, 2000-2012, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 077)
  - Programs, undated, 1 folder (Box 2, Folder 078)
- Clippings, 1975-2003, V.; Folder 79-84
  - Clippings, 1975, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 079)
  - Clippings, 1981-1988, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 080)
  - Clippings, 1991, 1993, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 081)
  - Clippings, 1996, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 082)
  - Clippings, 1997, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 083)
  - Clippings, 2003, 2007, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 084)
- Journal issues and publications, 1974-1997, VI.; Folder 85-92
  Alphabetically arranged by author.
  - Arts Midwest: Jazz Masters Journal, 1991-1995, 5 volumes (Box 3, Folder 085)
  - Arts Midwest: Midwest Jazz, 1995-1997, 5 volumes (Box 3, Folder 086)
  - Danner, Gregory J.: Nonlinear processor/multiresonant filter system for synthesis of musical tones, 1974-08, 51 pages (Box 3, Folder 087)
    Experimental Music Studios Technical Report no. 24 from University of Illinois School of Music.
  - Ferrari, Luc: Eléments d'un parcours confus…, circa 1997, 45 pages (Box 3, Folder 088)
    Bio-bibliography and discography accompanied by other material about Ferrari.
  - George, Anne: Suddenly, 1985, 21 pages (Box 3, Folder 089)
  - Northwestern University School of Music: Fanfare: Centennial issue no. 4, 1997, 61 pages (Box 3, Folder 090)
  - Rucktenwald, Thomas E.: Electronic synthesis of violin tones, 1974-06, 67 pages (Box 3, Folder 091)
    Experimental Music Studios Technical Report no. 22 from University of Illinois School of Music.
  - Second annual music computation conference: Proceedings, 1975-11, 4 volumes (Box 3, Folder 092)
- Scores, 1950-1994, VII.; Folder 93-125
  Contains scores by Gena and others.
  Alphabetically arranged by author and then by title.
  - Amirkhanian, Charles: His anxious hours, 1987, 1 folder (Box 4, Folder 093)
  - Amirkhanian, Charles: Metropolis San Francisco, 1986, 14 pages (Box 4, Folder 094)
  - Eastman, Julius: Crazy nigger, 1978, 13 pages; Photocopy of holograph. (Box 4, Folder 095)
    Accompanied by performance guide.
  - Eastman, Julius: Evil nigger, 1979, 29 pages; Photocopy of holograph. (Box 4, Folder 096)
  - Eastman, Julius: Gay guerrilla, 1979, 14 pages; Photocopy of holograph. (Box 4, Folder 097)
    Two copies.
  - Foss, Lukas: Curriculum vitae for solo accordion, 1978, 9 pages; Photocopy. (Box 4, Folder 098)
    Published by Pembroke Music.
  - Foss, Lukas: Thirteen ways of looking at a blackbird, 1980, 15 pages; Photocopy. (Box 4, Folder 099)
  - Gaburo, Kenneth: Antiphony IV, 1967, 16 pages; Ozalid copy. (Box 4, Folder 100)
    With accompanying notes.
  - Gena, Peter: Egg and the machine, 1967, 12 pages; Photocopy of holograph. (Box 4, Folder 101)
    For mixed chorus and piano, on a text by Robert Frost.
  - Gena, Peter: Modular fantasies, 1974, 2 scores (13 pages each) and 7 parts; Ozalid copy. (Box 4, Folder 102)
  - Gena, Peter: Modular fantasies II: sketches, circa 1975, 1 score; Pencil holograph. (Box 4, Folder 103)
    Composition served as Gena's dissertation in 1976.
  - Gena, Peter: O thou to whom the musical white spring: for flute, soprano, viola, guitar, 1968, 9 pages; Photocopy of holograph. (Box 4, Folder 104)
  - Gena, Peter: Syzygy, 1967, 15 pages; Ozalid copy. (Box 4, Folder 105)
  - Gena, Peter: Upon arriving in the city by the bay, 1970, 3 pages; Photocopy of holograph. (Box 4, Folder 106)
  - Higgins, Dick: Sonata for prepared piano, 1982, 8 pages (Box 4, Folder 107)
  - Higgins, Dick: Ten ways of looking at a bird, 1981, 15 pages (Box 4, Folder 108)
    For violin and harpsichord.
  - Johnson, Tom: 252: for piano, 1985, 12 pages (Box 4, Folder 109)
    Published by Two-Eighteen Press.
  - Johnson, Tom: Chord: for four instruments, 1984, 19 pages (Box 4, Folder 110)
  - Johnson, Tom: Septapede: for piano, 1975, 7 pages (Box 4, Folder 111)
    Published by Associated Music Publishers. Accompanied by catalogs of Johnson's works and a concert program.
  - Johnson, Tom: Symmetries, 1981, 64 pages (Box 4, Folder 112)
  - Lerman, Richard: Changing states 3: Duo version, 1992, 1 score (Box 4, Folder 113)
    Published by Frog Peak Music. For metal microphones, blowtorches, and other instrument.
  - Lerman, Richard: Travelon gamelon, 1991, 19 pages (Box 4, Folder 114)
    For three amplified bicycles. Published by Frog Peak Music.
  - Lombardi, Luca: Ai pedi del faro, 1987, 37 pages (Box 4, Folder 115)
    Published by Ricordi.
  - Lombardi, Luca: Bagatelles sans ry avec tonalité, 1992, 24 pages (Box 4, Folder 116)
  - Lombardi, Luca: Canzone di Greta, 1987, 15 pages (Box 4, Folder 117)
  - Lombardi, Luca: Jahreswechsel, 1994, 48 pages (Box 4, Folder 118)
  - Lombardi, Luca: Lied, 1988, 1 score (15 pages) and 2 parts (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - Lombardi, Luca: Ophelia-fragmente, 1983, 12 pages (Box 4, Folder 120)
    Published by Ricordi. Accompanied by works catalog.
  - Lombardi, Luca: Primo quartetto per archi: Quartett vom armen Mann, 1992, 15 pages (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - Miller, Thomas P.: Pines, 1973, 1 page; Photocopy. (Box 4, Folder 122)
  - Randall, J. K.: Gap 2-5, 1997, 51 pages (Box 4, Folder 123)
    Published by Open Space.
  - Rzewski, Frederic: Coming together, part 1, 1972, 17 pages; Photocopy. (Box 4, Folder 124)
  - Sapp, Allen: Five landscapes. Virginia; Cape Ann, 1950, 7 pages; Ozalid copy. (Box 4, Folder 125)
- Audio and video recordings, 1983-2010, VIII.; Folder 126-139
  Includes audio cassettes, compact discs, a VHS tape, and DVDs.
  Separated by format and then arranged alphabetically by creator.
  - Lerman, Richard: Within earreach, 1994, 1 compact disc (Box 5, Folder 126)
    Published by Artifact Records.
  - Lucier, Alvin: Theme, 1999, 1 compact disc (Box 5, Folder 127)
    Published by Lovely Music.
  - School of the Art Institute of Chicago: Sound projects Fall 2002, 2002, 1 compact disc (Box 5, Folder 128)
    Works by Anderko, Lange, Hanson, Winters, and Allard.
  - School of the Art Institute of Chicago: Sound projects Spring '97, 1997, 1 compact disc (Box 5, Folder 129)
    Works by Evans, Berkowitz, Moore, Clepper, Williams, Morgenstern, Deluge, Olan, Lechago, Dornberger, Peterson, Sinkinson, Collins, Gomez, and Whitt.
  - Arts Council of Lapland, Finland: Polararc, 1997, 1 CD-ROM (Box 5, Folder 130)
  - Battier, Marc: Untitled cassette, circa 1983, 1 audio cassette (Box 5, Folder 131)
    Includes works by, and collaborations with Jean-Paul Curtay.
  - Chadabe, Joel: Sample of playthings, 1980, 1 audio cassette (Box 5, Folder 132)
  - Martirano, Salvatore: Untitled cassette, 1982, 1 audio cassette (Box 5, Folder 133)
    Works by Salvatore Martirano and Ed Herrmann. "Selections from their KOPN performance November 1982."
  - Velasco, Alejandro: Urbe máxima, 1991, 1 audio cassette (Box 5, Folder 134)
    Released by Paraiso.
  - Cittadellarte-Fondazione Pistoletto: Universita delle ideee, 2000, 1 VHS video cassette (Box 5, Folder 135)
    PAL format.
  - Fontana, Bill: River sounding, 2010, 1 DVD (Box 5, Folder 136)
    VOB file format. Sound installation at Somerset House, London.
  - Fontana, Bill: Sonic shadows, 2010, 1 DVD (Box 5, Folder 137)
    VOB file format.
  - Fontana, Bill: Sound sculptures 1976-2007, circa 2010, 1 DVD (Box 5, Folder 138)
  - Fontana, Bill: Speeds of time, 2008, 1 DVD (Box 5, Folder 139)
    VOB file format. Version 1: London, 2004, Palace of Westminster; Version 2: London, 2008, Tate Britain and the BBC.
- Additions, 1970-2012, IX.; Folder 140-142
  Contains additions received after initial processing was completed.
  Arranged as received.
  - Correspondence, 1990-2012, 1 folder (Box 3, Folder 140)
  - Gena, Peter: Technical Report no. 7, National Science Foundation Project no. GK-14191: Musicol Manual, Version 1, May 1973, 132 pages (typescript); MUSical Instruction Composition Oriented Language for the 6400 Digital Computer. (Box 3, Folder 141)
    Accompanied by manuscript note from Lejaren Hiller.
  - Sinclair, John G., Jr.: Research report on audio display of brain waves, 21 August 1970, 45 pages; Written with Wendell R. Lipscomb. (Box 3, Folder 142)
    From the Research Department, Mendocino State Hospital, Talmage, California.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Eastman, Julius
Subjects
Music--20th century; Gena, Peter--Archives
Genres
Correspondence; Concert programs; Clippings (information artifacts); Scores; Sound recordings
Associated Material
Separated Material
The following published books were removed from the collection, either to be added to the general collection, or if duplicates, offered elsewhere.
Proceedings of the 1978 International Computer Music Conference, volume 1-2
Yamaha Avant Grand N3/N2 owner's manual
Espace Culturel Louis Vuitton: Anicroches: variations, choral et fugue Paris (France): Triangle/TRAM, 2012
Leopoldseder, Hannes: Prix Ars Electronica: International compendium for the computer arts Vienna (Austria; New York (New York): Springer, 1996
Leopoldseder, Hannes: Cyber Arts 2001 Vienna (Austria; New York (New York): Springer, 2001
Espace Culturel Louis Vuitton: Anicroches: variations, choral et fugue Paris (France): Triangle/TRAM, 2012
European Media Arts Festival: Media Arts Festival Osnabruck (Germany): European Media Arts Festival, 1998
Kunstforum International Mainz (Germany): Kunstforum International, 1989
Gerber, Karl: Mythos information: Welcome to the wired world: Ars electronica 95 Vienna (Austria; New York (New York): Springer, 1995
Ars Electronica: 1995, 1996, 1997, 2005
ISEA: Seventh International Symposium on Electronic Art: proceedings Rotterdam (Netherlands): ISEA Foundation, 1996
ISEA 97, Chicago: the eighth international symposium on electronic art: program guide, abstracts, events
The following posters were removed from the collection, either to be added to the Music Library poster collection, or if duplicates, offered elsewhere.
Mayor Byrne's New Music America '82
ISEA 97 Chicago: The 8th International Symposium of Electronic Art
1978 International Computer Music Conference
Northwestern University Contemporary Music Ensemble, Robert Moran, director: April 20, 1978
Chicago InterArts Ministry in cooperation with West Hubbard Gallery Music Series presents Moratorium - Manifesto: a performance minus. Sunday December 7 1980
School of the Art Institute of Chiacgo: Time Arts visiting artists